Well, we're trying to figure out what's the, what's going to be situation with the climate.
Give me some idea.
What is this group expertise?
Like any search people, obviously probably, because the previous presentation was great about search.
Any like the data people, analytical data people, we're so shy.
It's going to be a lot of talks about the analytics in this particular presentation.
Anyone using Kafka these days?
Question to the rest of the rest of the people, why you are not?
After this presentation, more people will be talking about and using Kafka.
My name is Victor.
I came from Confluent.
You know I've heard about Confluent before?
Confluent, his company, was founded by original creators slash Kafka.
And I work there as a principal self-provoc, meaning that I get to go places and talk
developers like you are about awesome things that
does. I'm a Java champion and wrote the book about Kafka. The most important
slide, probably, for today, have reporting in case if you want to return and experience
this awesome presentation one more time. Hopefully it's going to be awesome enough.
Video will be there, slides will be there, and there will be some links to some other
resources. Rumor has it, it's actually another rumor that there is a probably five
hours version of this presentation available. I did this live streams called
streaming frontiers at the council and developer YouTube channel where I went like in every
element of this presentation and built some demo applications so explains all the concept.
So today you will experience kind of like distilled version. You will get the gist of the
things. And if you want to like to go deeper with this, there will be speaking.com or that
will be a place where older sources you can buy. Now let's jump right into
to be the problem right now is terms of that.
But some problems that people might have in the past.
And usually when everything is simple, everything works,
you have one database, one business logic and you have some sort of front end.
And everything is it, that they did in one place.
You kind of, you know, SQL or your SQL is relatively simple to do.
Life is great until it's not.
Until your normal system is
are growing either amount of data. It's not going to fit in one place or logic.
It's become so complex that you need to start breaking things down. And someone said
microservices and things that we will start experiencing different type of problem.
I've been doing Kafka for the last almost 10 years now and I have a professional deformation.
So anything for me looks like a Kafka problem. So that's why I will be using Kafka as a kind
of like operational data store place where all the data are
engineering somehow. And simply because for all these years that I was talking about
Kafka, we were teaching people how to, for example, breaking down a melodical application
and use Kafka as a system of record that we can make these microservices to collaborate.
Also, it allows to change the way how you think about your data. You're not thinking about
tables, relationships, objects. Are you thinking about defense? Something that happens that can
describe maybe change.
the world or maybe there would be notifications of sort. And if you think about this,
the event as a concept is much more natural than object or entity or relationship,
because things happen in life. It's not objects, but we do have objects, but the most interesting
thing happened when something happens. Train, delays, orderships. You said something to your
significant other that you're not supposed to say. So again, this happened.
You can't change that. It is, it's already happened. So it is imputable. You can't change that.
And the only thing that you can do is to change the situation is to need another one. Say order
shifts, now order delivered, or, you know, you say something you're supposed to say,
apology issue, and depends on the other side, how they're going to be processing your event,
they will either accept it or not. It's changing the state of another system.
Now, here's one problem. It's a great tool for capturing things that happened, events,
but because of the nature of how the system is designed and what kind of like underlying data
structure is there, it's not very easy to quit this data. So inside the Kafka, inside the Kafka
this is to be the law. The vents are ordered by time. There's a very efficient way how
data would be written, how data would be consumed. You're reading from the beginning of the file,
you're writing to the end of the file. Simple, there's no random access, meaning that you
cannot create a particular key. There's no indexes. You cannot create this topic. You need to
always replay in order to get data. But what if we can reuse the knowledge that majority of the people
have with SQL. People tend to know how the SQL works and try to do something like this.
So that's the premise of this presentation. All right? So that's the idea. Okay, so our operational
date, everything, all events that happens in our system in Kafka, how are we going to be?
That's a quick refresher. If you need a refresher about Kafka,
your product writing file at the end, consumers read data from the data from the
point and from the point where they need to remember what kind of data they read or where
they were before the failure happened, there's a concept of offset.
Thinking about this as a as a bookmark in the book. You're reading the book from the beginning
to the end and somewhere in between. You want to make a pause. You close the book to put the
backmark, put this on the table. That's your offset. And you are a consumer in this particular
case. I think this is also, if you want to explain, so today you probably come back home to
your significant other. And they were asking you, honey, like, why you're so late?
You know what? After this meetup, we talk about Kafka. And honey, what's Kafka? And you
tell a story to them. So essentially, story about how the Kafka consumer group works. And in this
particular case, Kafka structured the data into partitions. So you don't have one large file.
You have multiple files that spread across multiple nodes, Kafka's distributed system.
And each of this partition will be placed on one particular server, one particular node.
And consumers, they will read partitions. They're not going to read whole topic.
Consumers, we're going to be reading, we're going to be reading topic.
In the concept of Kafka, there is a concept of consumer groups,
so consumers organized in the consumer groups that allows them to logically,
consumer group, controller, will be, um, that allows them to logically, uh, controller will be,
responsible for managing these consumers in this group.
How it works.
Tommy birds, consumer group controller, will be feeding sweet little worms
to our beautiful baby birds.
If you read this in the normal, not the
in the normal, this is like the adults talking to each other,
you will have, uh, consumer controller will assign partitions to
consumers and consumers. Can you do something?
I'm sorry, I'm trying to set it.
I think, I think it's going down.
Or something.
I don't know how you guys like sitting there.
I'm just forgetting.
I think it's going down just very slowly.
Maybe we can, yeah.
Can bring some refresh air or whatnot with that.
How much better thinking when I'm cold about the
So the consumer group coordinator will assign
partitions to consumer groups, consumers,
the consumer group. Say you have a topic with 10 partitions and you have one, two, three, four
consumers and consumer group.
So consumer group controller will be responsible to assigning to here to here,
maybe, or maybe three, three, three, one,
or maybe there's going to be something like two, two, two, three, three,
something like this.
That's a responsibility of algorithm that runs in the consumer control.
Why is that? Consumers are a unit of scalability of reads.
Kafka very efficient of reading data,
and because you will be able to scale how you're creating the data
that's you doing for consumers.
Now, if I continue this analogy,
if you want to increase throughput from your system,
reading the data faster,
there will be another baby bird hatch that joined consumer group,
and Miami Bird will stop a process of feeding these birds with worms,
and will rebalance.
If you ever use Kafka, you probably heard this concept of
consumer group rebalancing or rebalancing.
What is happening?
Well, our applications are that the Kafka is rebalancing.
In this case, consumer control
will be responsible to distribute.
So we have 10 partitions, 10 beta group worms,
and after that we have 1, 2, 3, 4,
or 5 consumers in the consumer group.
So each of them will get the two partitions.
Same thing works with another way around.
you, one of the baby birds died or fell out of tests, not saying died.
And in this case, rebalance is going to happen,
and the baby, my mommy bird will reassign.
So questions to the audience, with the question if you understood
how the consumer group works.
What's going to happen if we have 11 baby birds
and only 10 worms or 10?
warms or partitions?
What's going to happen with the, this one, any ideas?
Work with me. I understand it's hot and you want to sleep, yes.
I'm going to share?
No, not entirely.
It's kind of like this different topic, but this is not the word that I want to hear right now.
Partition?
Priorities.
Starvation.
Starvation. That's the word I want to hear right now.
Not like we have a,
not enough resources. But this particular baby bird will be starving because
there is a rule where the partitions will be consumed by one consumer only.
So in this case, there will be no kind of like a locking mechanism,
so multiple consumers will be kind of fighting for one partition,
data duplication, all this kind of stuff.
No.
So one consumer, if you have more consumers in consumer group, more than partitions,
one of them, they will be just a standing mind.
They will not do nothing.
They will be just participating in,
in the consumer group, they will be registered,
but they will not receive any data.
So why it's done, you can use it for over-provision your system,
and you have a consumer that would be sitting there,
just waiting in case of one of the failures,
it will take over really faster.
Actually, this is how some of the technology that's used for stream processing works.
For example, Graphics who uses this concept very active.
Anyway, two quiddies, or two type of quiddies,
I want to talk about today.
First one is typical your transaction query.
We have a credit card number.
Based on this credit card number, we want to get the list of full transactions.
We care about set of records.
We care about individual records.
We care about some of the lookups by key.
When we're talking about the analytical or a laptop of queries,
we really don't care about individual records anymore.
we more care about story.
So in operational or like transactional type of query,
we would be interested what we were, how much was spent in Whole Foods yesterday.
So in this case, you would select from the purchases where,
location, whole foods, and when it was like yesterday day.
And we will get the transaction that we spent.
With analytical queries, we're more interested in how much you were
spent the last month on the groceries.
So in this case, it's a bigger story because it's been involved multiple other
transactions and we want to get some results.
So it can include some aggregation.
It can have a segmentation across different dimensions.
So any type of analytical queries.
And I will try to kind of like distinguish whenever I will be talking about particular solution.
So it took me almost 15 minutes to do a preamble.
So you got to probably fully immersed in the idea of what I'm trying to.
to hear it. Does make sense or it doesn't make any sense?
I did mention this. I forgot to mention this, that I have a rule.
When there's a there's a silence in the auditory,
meaning that everything is clear or nothing is clear.
And because it's a silence in the audience, it's very difficult for me to figure out
if I'm doing good job or bad job explaining things. Maybe it's just like,
what this guy is talking about? I have that.
So speak up. I did this presentation multiple times.
I know this stuff.
I'm here for you to share some knowledge and you can learn something that will be applicable to your work in future.
Okay, deal?
I understand it's hot.
All right.
So we're probably not going to go through all these topics.
Like I said, there is a more comprehensive live stream.
Like every option in this list were broke down by me and I build the application.
I explain how it works in details.
So I'll try to go and scheme through the things, so it will create some interest for you.
So you will be able to kind of like go and drill down and find particular things.
So we're going to start with two things, which is what I like to call in-store brand,
something that comes with Kafka.
You basically don't use any third-party systems to do stuff.
We're going to talk quickly about streaming SQL databases.
We're going to talk about real-time all-up databases.
It sounds kind of like very similar-ish, but it's not entirely same.
Elastic search, obviously.
Elastic is hosting this event.
And also, Elastic can be one of the options to do query,
even though it's a system that does search.
There are some use cases where Elastic can be used as an analytical
quickly scheme through the...
I don't want to say something that is not something that is not
who or something that should not use.
But some things that I personally have less expertise,
specifically with all this data warehouses and stuff.
One of the interesting things that happened for a little years
is with the table formats and kind of like a rise of
data and technology that support that delay.
And we're going to talk a little bit about kind of like a
what we're doing in a consultant to solve this task.
Again, task here is that.
your operational data in Kafka, we want to get this into
getting operational queries or analytical queries.
All right? Okay.
Kafka Connect. Anyone using Kafka Connect these days?
Anyone heard about Kafka Connect before?
A few people.
Kafka Connect, it is a framework that is part of Apache Kafka.
As a vendor, usually vendor goes and write a connector
that will be running on top of this Kafka Connect.
And this connector
will be constantly doing something.
It can constantly pull the data from the source
and push data into Kafka,
or it can constantly reading data from Kafka
and push it to external system through some sort of connector.
In our case, what we're interested in in particular,
we're going to use what we call sync connector
that will be reading data from Kafka topic
and syncing into some simple use case, SQL-like database.
So the ways that you can query easily.
We can agree.
that the SQL went a very long way from 92, I would say.
And basically, when I was starting programming in Java,
I was thinking that I don't need to learn SQL.
Why would I?
I have a hybrid, I have GPA, like, I don't care.
He knows about hibernate who can, who calls hibernate these days?
But you know SQL, right?
So I think the SQL goes strong.
So you know how to create this?
you're using your favorite database.
And this is how you query stream.
You have a connector, pushing data to external system,
and you've queried this system.
You already know this technology, you know,
SQL, you know, Postgres, you know, MySQL,
you know, my SQL, you know,
any type of like database that you already know how to query.
You can do transaction queries easily.
You can find visual records.
Another quix, you still can do analogical queries.
It's not particular that it's done,
or maybe there's used to do certain optimization.
institutions, and digital indexes, all sorts of things.
But also you're maintaining another database.
So you're maintaining not only another database,
you're also maintaining infrastructure to run connector.
So connector is not the part of some Dranskopf.
It's another process that is part of open source project
but it's not the part of the property.
So you're running this as a external component.
And you need to make sure that connector itself is up to date.
You have a legislative version of this connector,
same way it's like some version of this connector.
the PC driver and all this kind.
So that's what I'm saying.
It's good full, kind of like a smaller use case.
It's kind of sometimes you can do this or like one-off use cases,
when you just need to quickly, you dump it into
Postgres, Dukui, and you know.
It's not very suitable for, you know, big,
intensive stream of data.
Or with something where you care about streaming aspect of the data.
Kafka Streams is another component
that ships with Kafka that you can use this.
It's a library.
It's not the tool.
It's not something that will be running.
It's a library that's using the right applications.
Not going to spend much time here.
I'm personally enjoying to talk about this because of JVM.
I love Java.
I like to talk about this.
It's amazing piece of technology.
But for people who are trying to just solve one problem,
Victor, we're still trying to, you know,
not trying to build another, I don't know,
what's the cool application,
not a spring boot application or whatnot.
not, we just want to query the stream.
Like, it's not in our interest.
So that's the fair, fair thing to say.
You go very deep in this case.
You're not, you're not the high level,
you're on the very low level with this.
You need to solve the problem how you deploy this.
You need to solve the problem, how you're going to maintain,
it's how you scale this applications,
and you end up basically building another.
another database. Interesting enough that when I like to start talking about SQL,
people who build Kafka streams, they understood that is a low-level library.
It's something that people like to build. And if you want to build new query,
you need to build new topology, being the new application, you've already deployed this.
And we have a disconnection because of the battery.
So, and the same people,
people who are building Kafka streams, they'll think, okay, so what if we find a way
how we can run SQL on top of Kafka streams?
Kafka streams is awesome and has a lot of capabilities to work with Kafka, lots of capabilities,
how Kafka can do multiple things together with Kafka streams.
So what about we come up with this idea that we can use Kafka streams, but we also build
the engine on top of this.
And this is where we're getting, actually, we're getting very, very close to, to
basically subject of our conversation.
We, at Confluent, maybe around 2000,
2018, probably we built this system.
We call it KSQL.
And this system we called Streaming Database.
And while we're building this, we came up with,
what's the word I'm looking for,
kind of sort of the three different characteristics
that can distinct the streaming database.
from the regular database.
So first of all, you want to make sure that Kafka
or any type of streaming source,
it's your first-class citizen.
You don't need to write connectors,
you don't need to bring something from outside,
you just need to point to Kafka and say,
hey, that's my copy.
First thing, Kafka is your source of first-class citizen.
Second, obviously, we will talk about this SQL.
We want to make sure that we can quickly,
effectively create this,
we can effectively,
acquitted this using SQL. And let's see if my, if a zoom will reconnect automatically,
hopefully, no, it did not. So I'll just completely
to zoom, so you will see my, you will see my screen. And third thing that we need to talk about
this is that, yes, Kafka provides the log, but in order to query this, we need to
all read this data from the very beginning.
We want to avoid this.
So we need to have some sort of like a persistency layer
where we can have store intermediate results.
Can you still?
Okay.
Let me see, that's okay, that should not bother me.
So what ended up with Kafka, KSQLDB was connected to Kafka.
you can use SQL to write this stream process.
or like your queries. But KSQL were tied to Kafka like too much. KSQL use Kafka
for storage, for storing intermediate results. It's because Kafka streams does that.
So we did this. It was cool. We're not talking about this guy anymore. So there are some other
products that are much better. Anyone heard about a thing called Rising Wave, maybe?
or maybe materialize.
Okay, a few people.
Interesting thing that when I called this two technologies,
there's another interesting aspect,
that number four, or like a three and a half.
It's not only you have a Kafka as a standard,
you know, connector, you just connect to Kafka SQL,
and you have a persistency or like materialized you
or some sort of place where we can have some sort of cacheing layer.
But also access to those databases, you need to use
also standard protocol and materialize and the rising wave and some other tools.
They use Postgres as wire protocol.
You can use existing tools to connect to the streaming database to do queries.
It's not meaning that you can write your posters communities on top of all this,
meaning that you can connect your existing tools, but you still need to write the queries
that are suitable for this system.
So it's very cool, as Markiply said, you might not understand.
at this right now, but your kid's going to log it.
Hopefully, we will have a databases in the future
because everyone is doing by coding this day,
so maybe not anymore.
So the streaming SQL start getting traction
for the last maybe like five years.
And it's still very cool technology, but there is still
maybe resentment, maybe there's some sort of kind of pushback
on the community, sometimes.
Sometimes new feels, it's not so new, five years, but anyway, so even when I ask you,
who heard about this, heard about that, like a few people only heard about this.
There is Apache Flink as well.
Anyone using Apache Flink in the room?
So Apache Flink, it is an open source project that was also conceived some time ago,
like quite like eight, eight years or maybe a little more.
as a university project in University of Berlin, I guess, where they were trying to research
how they're going to build a system that will have unified ways to query, batch, and stream data.
And Flink has SQL.
Flink, you can use, you can write Flink jobs using SQL, but it doesn't make Flink a streaming
database because Flink is the stream processing engines.
Flink doesn't have, like, storage.
It has a connector to Kafka, but it needs to have a little bit more.
You can build your sharing database using Flink, but by itself, Link is not showing that way.
What if we want to have getting like analytical stories at very low latency, very high data
freshness and high scalability? It feels like, you know, BS because feels like it's impossible
because so many, so many things. You want to have streaming data with high freshness,
meaning that we have data that is, all right, maybe seconds ago, that we can expose.
These database can be exposed directly to users, so it's going to be, like, high-scale
scale factor, so people will be hitting this the database, and run on top of, like, streaming
data with maybe 10 bytes of data.
Many of you know that Kafka was conceived in LinkedIn to solve some of the problems,
how they moved data between the systems.
specifically making, like, files available for Hadoop faster.
And over time, Kafka transform how LinkedIn think about data,
how the data lands inside, so everything happens in LinkedIn.
Everything that lands, it happens inside LinkedIn, it hands one big Kafka.
Every time you're logging there, you're liking your colleagues post, or you're saying congratulations
with your job or, I don't know, what else you're doing in the LinkedIn.
LinkedIn or like you're writing a job, the update of your job and saying, hey,
I'm accepted this position of vice president of very important things.
So all these things in LinkedIn create events.
And this event will be captured in one big Kafka.
So people LinkedIn thinking, okay, so we have all this shit ton of data, literally,
and we want to make some sense out of this data.
We want to increase engagement.
We want to make sure people use LinkedIn, not only just kind of
glorified place where they publish your resume, but maybe make it as a real social network
where people actually go in and doing something this.
And one of the first use cases they come up with is that who used my profile.
Have you ever used this feature?
Who used my profile?
And this feature, if you would notice, feature, it is analytical by nature because there's multiple
dimensions.
You can see multiple companies, role.
of people, you can see when, you can see the geography and all this kind of things.
But also, you want to get this information relatively fresh.
You don't care who did your profile two months ago.
Like, who bothered?
Like, a friend of mine used this information when he was going to interviews, and he kind of
like checking how good he's doing on the interview process.
You can see, like, multiple people from the same company, use his profile.
And I'm doing this thing right.
I digress, but this real-time all-app database that they built in order to serve this particular use case called the batch Pino.
And it has like a very nice integration with Kafka.
Data will arrive in Pino and will be available for QWER in a second.
So the freshness, the high-level freshness would be suitable for user-facing use cases.
For people, you know, one second is still consistent.
is real-time. We're not talking about real-time in sense of, you know, machines or computers,
but in the sense of people, if the data arrived two seconds ago, that's real-time for me.
Anyone using Apache Druids? Anyone, Apache, I think it's not Apache, Star Rocks, Apache Doris.
So all these databases, they all kind of like have this like real-time, real-time analytics,
you see.
Clickhouse.
Okay, a few people heard about. So that's the real-time lab.
I, yes, midi-second, midsseconds quid latency. They have a very powerful engine for indexes.
The system is pluggable. Things that John was talking about, including the vector indexes,
including the dictionary, like inverse index, all these things, also available in Pino.
So a geospatial index, vector index, all these things can be done on.
But in this case, complexity is growing because you, apart from the Kafka, you need to now maintain
another cluster. And this cluster is not easy to maintain because it has three different components,
one component for storage, one component for compute, and another component to make sure
that everything is worked together. Yes, you can use managed service. There's someone who will
manage this for you, but, you know, with great power.
comes a great headache for, you know, maintaining this infrastructure for yourself.
Companies like Uber, LinkedIn, and Uber-Eats specifically use Pino as to feeding some of the
real-time dashboard specifically for the part that Uber-Rids part that residents are owners using
feed-by a real-time all-up system. They cannot afford this because they know what they're doing,
but again, it can solve
this problem, but you're actually getting into a very painful place.
Elasticsearch is not analytical system. You can build dashboards that will give you some sort of
like analytical use cases, but essentially you will be relying very similar concepts. Most
likely you will be using the Elasticsearch connector that will be syncing data from Kafka
into Elasticsearch. You will be using Kibana or
how many languages to create the data right now in the last year? Like 12?
Man, yeah, it's a lot. It's like there was a new one recently. Yeah, it's the prom QL. We now support
on QL. Before that then. Before that it was ESQL. Esq. I love the ESQL and I'll tell you why.
So just just it's unrelated. Just let's do a quick break from all this nonsense. Let me show you
a quick SQL and you can tell me, say, let's see,
yeah. So, for example, for example, for example, so
where's my actual quiz? Let's let's take it on this one. Every time when you're
when you're reading a SQL, where do you start reading SQL?
You're not reading this from the top. Obviously, right?
because you need to find where you're quitting this from.
You need to start from the fraud.
And after that, all these things will make sense to you.
But it doesn't make any sense.
You start with select, gaining some stuff,
but you need to know where you're starting.
And this is where the SQL actually does this right,
because the first line of this query would be from.
And after that, you get the lines of the things that you will be quitting.
It was unrelated.
Hopefully, I'll give you a little bit of entertainment.
And I also shared my page when I was
I'm reading by SQL that starts not from the like normal people reading things.
I'm not going to talk much about Elastic Search.
I'm not big an expert, but we've built some of the integrations in the past with Elastic.
And there's a lot of things that Elastic does well.
And you learn this from the previous presentation.
But, you know, the things with maybe query the ideal lookups, lookups for the keys, something that
you're probably not going to do this there as well.
Now, data warehouses, your massive data warehouse that your organization might have like 20 years ago,
you know, someone bought this for a gazillion millions together with some hardware appliance,
now available in the cloud.
So you need to move the data to the cloud so you can start doing something like creating your data warehouses.
The pain for maintaining or like storing your data would be handled by the data
warehouse systems and you just go in there and just create it as data.
The problem is that the data cloud data warehouse or just in general warehousing technology
is not suitable for historically, not suitable for streaming.
It's always been batch oriented and the data needs to be there and properly index and things
like that.
So it's good for analytics maybe, not for real-time type of queries.
And again, same problems.
Yes, it can solve like a big data, the problem.
problem, but kind of like getting data on the real time, not so much.
Now, typical, typical scenario, how you're getting data from one system and move data to another system called ETL.
We're extracting data, which will transform this data into format that our, that's another system will receive.
Kafka can be used to be kind of your ATL system, and there's two things that needs to be done.
So when you extracting this data, you need to also know up front,
format of the data of receiving system, that's this job to get one place to another.
And for some time, the people who were doing a lot of data integration thinking,
okay, in many cases, we actually don't know how this data would be created.
We don't know how this data would be used in the future.
We need to make sure that data will be available for someone, so they will be, you know,
whenever they need, they will go and reach.
So this is how the ETL transformed to ELT,
from the system in some sort of format,
store it somewhere, and only when you're ready to read this data,
consume this data, you will apply schema and you will figure out how to read this.
And this is the kind of like a typical data, like,
depends on freshest of the data, and depends on how often you're using
this data like can't become data swamp, because there will be like a lot of all data
and no one is using this, because there's no good way to use this data.
And in order to use this data,
and in order to use this data,
or at least understand from perspective of metadata data,
where it's data stored and how this data would be used.
The format of the metadata,
there's some sort of standard types,
and a lot of work has been done on the database side of things
and snowflakes and things.
Netflix built this awesome format called Iceberg
and they donated to this two bachelor foundation,
and many people started adopting.
this format for their music.
So Iceberg, it's a format.
Anyone using Apache Iceberg today for their analytical needs?
Anyone using Data Lake if Databricks evolved in the room?
Why so shy? It's awesome.
And yeah, so you have this place, this data lake.
Typically, it's going to be, in the past it was HGFS these days,
it's S3, have a bunch of files.
there usually these files in some sort of format like the Parcate or maybe it's Avro.
And what the open table format gives creates the metadata on top of this.
So you will be able to go in query.
So all these files, now we'll have a logical structure.
They can be represented as a table, so you can do queries.
You can do some awesome things like, I don't know if you have a slide like this.
So for example, Iceberg has a very cool feature that allows you kind of like a time travel
and get the snapshot of your data,
how these tables would look like, you know,
day ago or week ago.
Technically is possible.
Practically, it's very difficult
because you need to create a lot of extra storage
to store all these snapshots.
Not the topic of this presentation.
There is a brilliant presentation on the subject.
But this also creates interesting use case.
So now, analytical systems, they can, and may,
of them can now read iceberg natively.
You can have your snowflake, you can have a Trino,
you can have .DB, you can have Spark, what have you,
to read iceberg tables.
So what if, instead of all this kind of like ETL stuff
and the moving data around in different systems,
what if we'll give you ability to query topics,
Kafka topic as an iceberg table?
So this is exactly what we did at Conflint.
We built this technology called Tableflow.
It does exactly as I said.
Data in Kafka topic with the one change of configurations
become available for query from any type of system
that can query iceberg tables.
It can be Snowflake, it can be Athena,
it can be atrinos, spark, flame, what happened.
And in this case, ETL part is hidden.
So ETL part is something that you're not doing.
So basically we merging our operational tier
and making this
available for analytical tier.
Our streaming data is still our operational data,
and the iceberg would be our place
where the people start, so start quitting this.
In reality, it's not that simple, you know?
Remember a notebook Brian Gossom and the traditional Academes?
What do you want?
It's not that simple.
In reality, you probably will be using multiple
different aspects. Thankfully, Kafka provides this way.
So Kafka, as many people started using Kafka as a messaging system,
and they quickly realize that it's actually not exactly like messaging system,
because Kafka stores, Kafka remembers, Kafka stores the data when the message was consumed
for one system, it's still available for consumption to another system.
And maybe in your organization, you will be using multiple different technology
to solve this problem that I just described, creating this data.
You can feed some dashboards using the license,
in Kibana, you can query graphic data if you're interested in getting more kind of like a snapshot of operational data,
or you're running into some sort of like a batch analytics using data links.
Before we finish this presentation, I will give you quick a kind of like a framework
that you can use to figure out, like, which technology to use.
I'm not going to read this from slides.
You can take a photo.
you can remember this or you remember slides will be published.
But essentially, there's no one size of it.
I usually do this disclaimer at the very beginning of presentation
that there's not going to be a right answer at the end.
I forgot to do this, but there would be no right answer.
Everything needs to be solved, like, per use case basis,
because sometimes some of the technology will work for you.
Some of the technology will not work in the legal use things.
Three things that also needs to be considered.
I really love to talk.
about technologies, the different software pieces, hardware pieces.
It's great.
I don't talk about this.
But most importantly, many problems in the organizational world,
they're not technology problems.
You know, where to find the people who know all this stuff,
like people have experience to building this type of system.
So how you find the experts is very important.
Personally, I don't think.
Do I have a slide like this?
if I have a slide like this.
Yeah.
I'll talk about this in a second.
Second thing is that performance.
I came from the Eastern European communities.
They historically very geeky about performance,
kind of like going deeper and making things faster,
because I don't know, we couldn't afford faster computers,
so we need to optimize the software and making sure that we squeeze in every bit
and bite from things available for us.
So for some people, it's important.
For some people, it's not.
A few months ago, I was at the panel with a representative from,
so I'm representative from the streaming world,
the person was representative from kind of like a batch world.
And obviously for me, I'm meeting with customers who care about real-time,
who are interested in building systems that could be responsible in real-time,
and thought for them, their customers,
you said, our customers can wait 10 minutes, it's fine.
There's nothing they say about this.
It's, they find, they're okay with this.
And that's kind of like, that's the most important thing,
that it's not about technology.
Yeah, Kafka is awesome.
Yeah, we can scale this for the millions of events in the second.
Yeah, we can build the iceberg tables and the who did this super fast.
But if it's not, you know,
thread of the needle or not, like pushing the envelope, it doesn't matter.
Like, I would not be able to convince.
And third is the most important thing is that, you know,
why we're all here.
It's the community.
The reason why Kafka, for example,
become like super popular and,
super useful is because the community of engineers
in Silicon Valley were able to share their knowledge.
So the people in the LinkedIn, they went and shared
one of the meetups, talk about what they built
in order to speed up their Hadoop jobs.
People in Uber look at this and say,
hey, we actually can use this.
We can use when we're building this small application
that will be, you know, people will be using
to call a taxi and things like that.
So, and they start working together.
It's good that.
LinkedIn engineering has this brilliant culture
of encouraging open source.
A lot of open source projects came from LinkedIn
or LinkedIn engineers actually contribute to this.
From my personal story about community,
the language, my first program language,
was not Java, was nothing,
not CBO, but it was a Pascal.
Anyone doing Pascal or remember what Pascal is?
It's cool language.
It's also a language.
language. And the reason why I learn about this
is not because it was cool or sexy or like someone is
paying like a good amount of money.
No, I just get the guy next door who can answer my stupid questions,
how I can start, how I can do things.
And that's also important.
And the same thing happened with the Silicon Valley
when the people start doing coffee and start talking about job
to other people.
Community 1.
Any scholar people here?
Yeah, because the scholar people will tell
It's like, you need to have PhD to get to our community first.
And after that you can ask questions.
Yes, I still have a grudge to scholar community
and I'm not going to shut up until...
I see this sticker.
Yay! Yes. No, no Scala.
The jokes aside, it's personal story.
I personally was hurt when I was trying to learn Scala,
was rejected from this glorious community, never came back.
But I find my people in the data world, in the data engineering and streaming.
All right.
So, why?
But you can try, today's Thursday, I'm not necessarily asking you to try anything tomorrow, but maybe on Monday.
If you're interested, you can check the website called developer.comflin.io,
where we can find examples that allows you to build alternative queries with competition.
Or maybe you want to try this very cool piece of technology written in Rust.
Why I say this?
But sometimes it's the big selling point for people, rise in wave.
It's a great tool if you want to try.
to do stuff like this. For example, if you just need to read data from Kafka immediately,
that's the whole connector code. There is nothing here that you need to let me close this.
Well, can I close this?
Yes, it's just here.
It connects to Kafka, specifies a format that it can fetch from the Schumer Registry,
and selects what kind of fields we get into it.
from there. That's it. That's your whole Kafka connector. And after that, you will
be able to do materialized to you. That will be constant update. It's very cool technology.
I highly recommend to check it out. It's very fun to play around.
Even though if maybe not necessarily will be 100% related to your work you do it right now.
Trying to build something with Pino.
Somewhere on the internet, there is a free training materials that yours truly
recorded and the created whole course about
Pino and how it can work with Kafka. It was pretty cool.
Yeah. And if you want to play around, you can play around with the table flow as well.
Again, develop little Kafka.
That's a free educational resource where you can find a lot of things about streaming,
not necessarily related to this particular subject, but things may be something
that you would be interested in how to count number of messages in the topic.
You don't know how to go there, you can find answer there.
Stream Frontiers. It's my live stream show.
So it's been a while since I've been alive because I was other things,
but I need to come back and do some other things.
It's pretty cool.
Slides will be available here.
Speaker 2Gammer.
I will see if the videos also will be available.
And with this, my name is Richard Gamov, and as always, have a nice day.